Register to the Archimandrite Amvrosii papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Archimandrite Amvrosii papers
1920-1977
2008C45
Hoover Institution Archives
6 microfilm reels (0.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, and photographs, relating to the Russian Orthodox Church and to Russian émigré affairs.
Amvrosii, Archimandrite (Konovalov), 1890-1971.
Access
The collection is open for research
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Alternative Forms of Material Available
A portion of the collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Original Materials
Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Chronology
1890 Born Victor Andreevich Konovalov, St. Petersburg, Russia
1920 Evacuated to Constantinople
1963 Author, Istina i apostasiia
1971 Died, Jordanville, NY
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection contains the papers of Viktor Andreevich Konovalov, a self-proclaimed missionary of Canada in emigration, and later a Russian Orthodox monk and abbot of the Pokrov Skete in Bluffton, Alberta, Canada. Konovalov's rich Correspondence includes letters to and from prominent hierarchs of the Russian diaspora, located throughout the world, and provides a significant source for information on Russian Orthodoxy in North America in the Interwar years as well as in the immediate aftermath of World War II. In addition, Konovalov's papers present a valuable record of the functioning and economic struggles of the Pokrov Skete in Alberta, Canada.
The Speeches and Writings file reflects the personal interests of Fr. Amvrosii, which included eschatological research as well as studies of holy fathers and church history. The Subject File materials relating to the history of the Russian Orthodox Church Outside Russia, including an almost complete collection of "Tserkovnyia viedomosti," the official ecclesiastical periodical of the Russian Orthodox Church Outside Russia during the Interwar years.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Speeches and writings, and Photographs
Biography
Victor Andreevich Konovalov was born in St. Petersburg in 1890, joined the White Army during the Civil War in Russia in 1918, and was forced to evacuate to Constantinople in 1920. From 1921 to 1923 Konovalov was actively involved in the Russian Orthodox Church in Constantinople. He soon immigrated to Canada, where he became a self-proclaimed missionary. Konovalov subsequently became a Russian Orthodox monk and abbot of the Pokrov convent in Bluffton, Alberta, Canada.
Archimandrite Amvrosii (Konovalov) died in 1971 at Holy Trinity Monastery in Jordanville, N.Y.
Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'.; Russians--Canada.
- Biographical File, 1920-1962. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes ecclesiastical documents, military record, will. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Ecclesiastical certificates, 1922-1923 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Military record, 1920 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Will, 1938-1962 (Folder 1: 3)
- Correspondence, 1922-1965 and undated.
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - General
      - 1923-1949 and undated (Folder 1: 4)
      - 1950-1964 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Mount Athos, 1924-1961. (Folder 1: 6)
      Includes correspondence with various monks from different monasteries on Mount Athos
    - Russian Orthodox Church
      - 1923-1949 and undated (Folder 1: 7)
      - 1950-1963 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Afanasii (Martos), Archbishop, 1961 and undated (Folder 1: 9)
  - Aggei (?), Archimandrite, 1947-1961 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Aleksandrov, Nikolai N., 1947-1961 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Anastasii (Gribanovskii), Metropolitan, 1922-1962 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Andreevskii, Ivan Mikhailovich, 1949-1962 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Antonii (Khrapovitskii), Metropolitan, 1932-1933 and undated (Folder 2: 3)
  - Antonii (Sinkevich), Archbishop, 1961-1965 and undated (Folder 2: 4)
  - Apollinarii (Koshevoi), Archbishop, 1927-1939 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Ariadna (Michurina), Abbess, 1948-1956 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Arsenii (Chakhovtsev), Bishop, 1930-1931 and undated (Folder 2: 7)
  - Averkii (Taushev), Archbishop, 1955-1965 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Baranova-Popova, ?, 1950 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Bari, Sofiia Nikolaevna, 1947-1950 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Borzov, Nikolai Viktorovich, 1951 and undated (Folder 2: 11)
  - Brazol', Boris L'vovich, 1948 and undated (Folder 2: 12)
  - Buketov, Feofan, Reverend, 1948-1950 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Burdykov, Georgii, Reverend, 1933-1949 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Chagaida, Onufrii, 1948-1951 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Chernavin, Ioann, Reverend, 1946-1948 and undated (Folder 2: 16)
  - Chervinskii, Evgenii, Reverend, undated (Folder 2: 17)
  - Danil'chik, Mikhail, Reverend, 1931-1933 and undated (Folder 2: 18)
  - Demchuk, Mr., 1947 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Demidov, Vasilii, Reverend, 1947-1948 and undated (Folder 2: 20)
  - Deputatov, Nikolai Mikhailovich, 1941 and undated (Folder 2: 21)
  - Diakonik, Ilarion, 1949 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Dionisii (Valedinskii), Metropolitan, 1932 and undated (Folder 2: 23)
  - Dydik, Leontii and Anna, undated (Folder 2: 24)
  - Feodosii (Samoilovich), Archbishop, 1931-1965 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Feofan (Bystrov), Archbishop, 1932 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Filaret (Voznesenskii), Metropolitan, 1965 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Gerasim (Shmal'ts), Archimandrite, (1946-1951 and undated (Folder 2: 28)
  - Grabbe, Georgii, Reverend, 1952-1959 (Folder 2: 29)
  - Grigor', Ioann, Reverend, 1932-1965 and undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Grinenko, Vladimir Kharitonovich, 1955 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Holy Trinity Monastery, 1946-1960 and undated (Folder 3: 3)
  - Iakushin, Petr Mitrofanovich, 1947-1949 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Ieronim (Chernov), Archbishop, 1938-1948 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Ioasaf (Skorodumov), Archbishop, 1922-1958 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Kalinovskii, Anton Grigorievich, 1947-1951 and undated (Folder 3: 7)
  - Kappanadzi, Ioason, Reverend, 1946-1948 and undated (Folder 3: 8)
  - Kharit, Filip Vasilievich, 1946 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Kiziun, Aleksandr, Reverend, 1928 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Kokhanik, Petr, Reverend, 1947-1952 and undated (Folder 3: 11)
  - Komarnitskii, Nikanor, Reverend, 1932-1961 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Konon-Ivashkevich, Mr., 1951 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Konstantin (Zaitsev), Archimandrite, 1935-1962 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Kontsevich, Elena Iur'evna and Ivan Mikhailovich, 1948-1963 and undated (Folder 3: 15)
  - Krupenskii, Aleksandr Nikolaevich, 1927-1930 (Folder 3: 16)
  - Kryzhanovskii, Nikolai Antonovich, 1940 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Kutepov, Aleksei Pavlovich, 1929 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Kuterev, Boris Leonidovich, 1950 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Ladinskii, Leonid, Reverend, 1956 and undated (Folder 3: 20)
  - Lavr (Shkurla), Abbot (later Archbishop and Metropolitan), 1958-1961 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Lebedev, Manuil, Reverend, 1932 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Legkii, Ioann, Reverend, 1951 and undated (Folder 3: 23)
  - Lekhovich, Vladimir Andreevich, 1928-1929 and undated. (Folder 3: 24)
    Includes newspaper clipping and letter from General A. P. Kutepov to Lekhovich
  - Leontii (Bartoshevich), Archimandrite, 1945-1948 and undated (Folder 3: 25)
  - Leontii (Filippovich), Archbishop, 1957-1961 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Levitskii, N., Reverend, 1951 (Folder 3: 27)
  - Lototskii, Dimitrii Vasilievich, undated (Folder 3: 28)
  - Maloshev, Mr., 1949 (Folder 3: 29)
  - Mannerheim, Carl Gustaf Emil, 1939 (Folder 3: 30)
  - Maslov, Diodor Nikolaevich, 1949 (Folder 3: 31)
  - Meletii (Zaborovskii), Metropolitan, 1941 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Merzheevskii, Vladimir Danilovich, 1957-1963 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Mikhailov, Vasilii, Reverend, undated (Folder 4: 3)
  - Miller, Evgenii Karlovich, General, 1929 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Mishukov, Aleksandr Feodorovich, 1943-1947 and undated (Folder 4: 5)
  - Morozov, Ivan, 1933-1934 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Nikolai (Karpov), Bishop, 1932 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Nikon (Rklitskii), Bishop, 1936-1964 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Panteleev, Sergii, Reverend, 1940-1961 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Panteleimon (Rudyk), Archbishop, 1955 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Platon (Rozhdestvenskii), Metropolitan, 1926 and undated (Folder 4: 11)
  - Poliakov, Sergei, 1924 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Polonskii, Sergei Pavlovich, 1959-1965 and undated. (Folder 4: 13)
    Includes photograph of Archimandrite Amvrosii (Konovalov)
  - Pol'skii, Mikhail, Reverend, 1949-1957 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Rimarenko, Adrian, Reverend (later Bishop), 1959-1962 (Folder 4: 15)
  - Romanov, V. S., 1949-1950 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Rybakov, Nikolai Pavlovich, 1932-1959 (Folder 4: 17)
  - Sabo, Georgii, 1948-1952 (Folder 4: 18)
  - Savva (Sarachevich), Bishop, 1958-1961 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Serafim (Ivanov), Archbishop, 1932-1961 (Folder 4: 20)
  - Serafim (Svezhevskii), Bishop, 1951 (Folder 4: 21)
  - Shaliakin, Feodor Gavrilovich, 1946-1952 (Folder 4: 22)
  - Shaposhnikov, Vasilii, Reverend, 1940-1941 (Folder 4: 23)
  - Sharov, Nikolai Aleksandrovich, 1946 (Folder 4: 24)
  - Shomin, M. I., 1948-1949 (Folder 4: 25)
  - Solada, Mikhail, 1958 (Folder 4: 26)
  - Sul'zhikov, Aleksandr Viktorovich, 1927-1933 (Folder 4: 27)
  - Sumarokov, Evgenii Nikolaevich, 1941 (Folder 4: 28)
  - Starukhin, Marko, 1947-1948 (Folder 4: 29)
  - Stepanov, Nikolai, 1949 (Folder 4: 30)
  - Synod of Bishops of the Russian Orthodox Church Outside Russia, 1928-1959 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Teliatnikov, N., undated (Folder 5: 2)
  - Tikhon (Liashchenko), Bishop, 1932 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Tikhon (Troitskii), Archbishop, 1931-1961 (Folder 5: 4)
  - Tsuglevich, Aleksandr, Reverend, 1930-1935 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Turianitsa, Mikhail Il'ich, 1964 and undated (Folder 5: 6)
  - Urusova, Nataliia Vladimirovna, 1958-1961 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Varshavskii, Sigizmund, 1948-1951 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Vdovichenko, Petr, Reverend, 1932-1933 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Venedikt (Bobkovskii), Bishop, 1951 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Vitalii (Maksimenko), Archbishop, 1939-1951 (Folder 5: 11)
  - Vitalii (Ustinov), Bishop, 1934-1967 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Vorobets, Sergei Lukich and Dominika Iosifovna, 1946-1952 and undated (Folder 5: 13)
  - Zavalishin, Boris Arkadievich, 1947 and undated. (Folder 5: 14)
    Includes signed typescript entitled "Nash pozor"
  - Znamenskii, Aleksandr, Reverend, 1946-1951 and undated (Folder 5: 15)
  - Znamenskii, Georgii, 1947 and undated (Folder 5: 16)
  - Zosima (?), Archimandrite, 1948-1949 and undated (Folder 5: 17)
- Speeches and Writings, 1922-1977 and undated.
  Announcements, appeals, articles, greetings, notebooks, notes, open letters, and sermons, arranged chronologically by title
  - General
    - Announcements, appeals, greetings, 1946-1961 and undated. (Folder 5: 18)
      Typescripts, printed copy and holographs
    - Articles, 1951-1963 and undated. (Folder 5: 19)
      Typescripts
    - Letters to the editor, 1932-1961 (Folder 5: 20)
    - Notebook, undated. (Folder 5: 21)
      Holograph
    - Notes
      - General, 1933-1964 and undated. (Folder 5: 22)
        Holographs and typescripts
      - Lives of saints, undated. (Folder 5: 23)
    - Open letters, 1922-1933. (Folder 5: 24)
    - Sermons, 1945-1962 and undated. (Folder 5: 25)
    - Speeches, undated. (Folder 5: 26)
      Typescript
  - "Fra Ieronim Savaranola – neponiatyi i nepriznannyi sviatoi," Russkaia zhizn', 1977, Nos. 8762-8778. (Folder 5: 27)
    Printed copy
  - "Istina i apostasiia,", 1963. (Folder 5: 28)
  - "Nastavleniia ieroskhimonakha Amvrosiia, startsa Optinoi pustyni,", 1940. (Folder 5: 29)
    Typescript. Includes foreword by V. Konovalov and dedication to Hierodeacon Avenir
  - "Sobytiia poslednikh dnei po svidetel'stvu sviatykh prorokov,", undated. (Folder 5: 30)
- Subject File, 1922-1963 and undated. (Box 6)
  Curriculum vitae of diocesan clergy, brochures, inventories, leaflets, minutes, notes, periodical, personal documents and certificates, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Nezym, Semen Semenovich, 1924. (Folder 6: 1)
    Personal documents and certificates
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov' Zagranitsei
    - General - Leaflets, 1936-1963 and undated (Folder 6: 2)
    - Alberta, Canada, 1931-1959 and undated. (Folder 6: 3)
      Includes curriculum vitae of diocesan clergy, lists of relics held at Pokrov skete in Bluffton, Alberta, minutes of diocesan meetings, liturgical notes
    - Iz dieianii arkhiereiskago sobora Russkoi Pravoslavnoi Tserkvi Zagranitsei, 1960 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Tserkovnyia viedomosti, 1922-1930. (Folder 6: 5-8)
      Includes notes on missing issues and provenance
- Photographs, 1948-1963 and undated. (Folder 6: 9)
  Ten prints depicting Archimandrite Amvrosii (Konovalov)